Chapter 63. The crotch.
Out of the trunk the branches grow. Out of them the twigs. So in productive
subjects grow the chapters.
The crotch alluded to on a previous page deserves independent mention. It is a
notched stick of a peculiar form, some 2 feet in length, which is perpendicularly
inserted into the starboard gunnel near the bow, for the purpose of furnishing a
rest for the wooden extremity of the harpoon, whose other naked barbed end
slopingly projects from the prow.
Thereby the weapon is instantly at hand to its hurler, who snatches it up as
readily from its rest as a backwoodsman swings his rifle from the wall. It is
customary to have two harpoons reposing in the crotch, respectively called the
first and second irons.
But these two harpoons, each by its own cord, are both connected with the line.
The object being this, to dart them both, if possible, one instantly after
the other, into the same whale, so that if in the coming drag one should draw
out, the other may still retain a hold.
It is a doubling of the chances. But it very often happens that owing to the
instantaneous violent convulsive running of the whale upon receiving the first
iron, it becomes impossible for the harpooner, however lightninglike in his
movements to pitch the second iron into him. Nevertheless, as the second iron is
already connected with the line, and the line is running, hence that weapon must
at all events be anticipatingly tossed out of the boat. Somehow and somewhere
else the most terrible jeopardy would involve all hands tumbled into the
water. It accordingly is in such cases.
The spare coils of box line mentioned in a preceding chapter making this feat in
most instances prudently practicable.
But this critical act is not always unattended with the saddest and most fatal casualties.
Furthermore, you must know that when the second iron is thrown overboard, it
thenforth becomes a dangling sharpedged terror, skittishly curvetting about both
boat and whale, entangling the lines or cutting them, and making a prodigious
sensation in all directions. Nor in general is it possible to secure it
again until the whale is fairly captured and a corpse.
Consider now how it must be in the case of four boats, all engaging one
unusually strong, active, and knowing whale, when, owing to these qualities in
him, as well as to the thousand concurring accidents of such an
audacious enterprise, eight or 10 loose second irons may be simultaneously
dangling about him. for of course each boat is supplied with several harpoons
to bend onto the line should the first one be ineffectually darted without
recovery. All these particulars are faithfully narrated here as they will
not fail to elucidate several most important however intricate passages in
scenes hereafter to be painted.